Guide to the Ronald Anthony Cross Papers, 1971-2019 and undated RL.11756
David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library
Ronald Anthony Cross papers
1971-2019 and undated
David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library
Cross, Ronald Anthony
RL.11756
9 Linear Feet
Ronald Anthony Cross was an American science fiction and fantasy author. Collection includes a wide array of Cross' creative work, including short stories and novelettes, poems, essays, song lyrics, novels, and copies of his published work. In addition there is research he conducted for his published books, and often material related to the publishing process, including tracking sheets, correspondence, contracts, reviews, and royalty statements. Material dated past Cross' death has to do with republishing agreements.
Arrangement
Organized into the following series: Writings, Research, and Correspondence.
Biographical / Historical
Ronald Anthony Cross was born on 1937 September 12 in Hollywood California and died on 2006 March 1, in Sherman Oaks, Los Angeles, California. He was an American science fiction and fantasy author.
Access Restrictions
Collection is open for research.
Provenance
The Ronald Anthony Cross Papers were received by the David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library as a gift in 2019.
Collection Overview
Includes a wide array of Cross' creative work, including short stories and novelettes, poems, essays, song lyrics, novels, and copies of his published work. In addition there is research he conducted for his published books, and often material related to the publishing process, including tracking sheets, correspondence, contracts, reviews, and royalty statements. Material dated past Cross' death has to do with republishing agreements.
Authors, American -- 20th century; Authors, American -- 21st century; Authors and publishers; Science fiction, American; Fantasy fiction, American; Short stories, American; American fiction -- 20th century; American fiction -- 21st century; Fantasy fiction; Science fiction; Fantasy fiction; Science fiction; Cross, Ronald Anthony
- Writings, 1971-2005 and undated
  Scope and Contents
  Includes a wide array of Cross' creative work, including short stories and novelettes, poems, essays, song lyrics, novels, and copies of his published work. Drafts and copy edited versions of his writings are often accompanied by a variety of other material, including Cross' tracking documents, correspondence, contracts, royalty payments, reviews, photocopies of the published piece, and other items related to the publishing process.
  - Stories and novelettes
    - The Adventures of Lance the Lizard, 1993 (Box 1)
    - Air Kwatz, 1980 (Box 1)
    - Altogether Different, 1976-1989 (Box 1)
    - All the Way to Teelee Town, 1994 (Box 1)
    - Angel Thoughts, 1989-1990 (Box 1)
    - Apartments, 1984 (Box 1)
    - The Beautiful People are Dying Off, 1976-1988 (Box 1)
    - The Birds are Free, 1974-1977 (Box 1)
    - Born Killer, 1975-1982 (Box 1)
    - Carrot Sticks, 1990 (Box 1)
    - A Citizen of 3V, 1983-1988 (Box 1)
    - The Cloud Driver, 1973-1984 (Box 1)
    - Costume Party, 1986-1988; 1 Linear Feet 1 turtle (Box 1)
      Terminal turtle
    - Conman and Le Guin satires and King Kong and Fellowship of the Ring, 1976 (Box 1)
      Series contains all the descendants of Noah
    - The Coutnry Store, 1987-1989 (Box 1)
    - The Dolls: A Tragic Romance, 1979-1997 (Box 1)
    - Double Trouble, 1976-1989 (Box 1)
    - Down the Hatch, 1984-1989 (Box 1)
    - Emaron or the Jewel Thief, Part 2, Or Water Kwatz, Part 2, 1984-1991; 1 items (Box 1)
    - An Entertainment (new version), 1987-1997 (Box 1)
    - An Entertainment (old version), 1975-1990 (Box 1)
    - Every Trembling Blossom, Every Singing Bird, 1988-1992 (Box 1)
    - The Exchange, 1973-1984 (Box 1)
    - The Experiment, 1987 (Box 1)
    - The Exterior Decorator, 1974-1982 (Box 1)
    - Fake Gods- Fake Twilight, 1975-1978 (Box 1)
    - The Fool, 1987-1988 (Box 1)
    - The Forming of the Brotherhood of the Dome, 1974 (Box 1)
    - The Forever Summer, 1982-1990 (Box 1)
    - The Front Page, 1988 (Box 1)
    - Gettign Off, 1974 (Box 1)
    - The Gladiator and the Priest, 1974-1976 (Box 1)
    - Glock Speak (new version), 1987-1995 (Box 1)
    - Glock Speak (old version), 1976-1986 (Box 1)
    - Golden Down, 1984 (Box 1)
    - The Gods are in the Streets (new version), 1988-1997 (Box 1)
    - Grovel for Tears, 1993 (Box 1)
    - Gruesome Twosome, 1976-1978 (Box 1)
    - Hanging out with Bitsy, 1990 (Box 1)
    - The Heart (revised), 1990-1995 (Box 1)
    - The Heart (old version), 1976-1986 (Box 1)
    - Hermes and the Magic Helmet, 1988-1990 (Box 1)
    - The Heavenly Blue Answer, 1985-1995; 2 folders (Box 2)
    - Hotel Mind Slaves, 1983-1985 (Box 2)
    - In the Garden, 1975-1979 (Box 2)
    - I Wonder What I'm Watching Now, 1989-1992 (Box 2)
    - The Initiate, 1983-1988 (Box 2)
    - It Can't Happen Here, 1975-1990 (Box 2)
    - Jack's Cafe, 1986-1990 (Box 2)
    - The Jewel Thief, 1972-1973 (Box 2)
    - Johnny's Inferno, 1989-1993 (Box 2)
    - Joy of Genre Cooking, 1985-1991 (Box 2)
    - Justifiable Homicide, 1986-1994 (Box 2)
    - The Last Ugly Man (new version), 1990 (Box 2)
    - The Last Ugly Man (old version), 1987-1990 (Box 2)
    - The Magician, 1988-1991 (Box 2)
    - The Man in the Red Suit, 1992 (Box 2)
    - The Man Who Saves the World, 1972-1984 (Box 2)
    - Mantra, 1984-2005 (Box 2)
    - The Mayflower Sinks, 1975-1980 (Box 2)
    - Monkey See, 1985-1990 (Box 2)
    - Moon Madness, 1984-1987 (Box 2)
    - Morely's Virus, 1979-1985 (Box 2)
    - New Improved Beach Ball, 1987-2005 (Box 2)
    - New Olympus, 1980-1985 (Box 2)
    - The One Way Man, 1974-1983 (Box 2)
    - Out of Spite, 1974-1985 (Box 2)
    - Paraoiadroid, 1985-1989 (Box 2)
    - Patterns, 1975-2005 (Box 2)
    - Pick up the Pieces, 1975-1980 (Box 2)
    - The Poor Little Black Girl, 1984-1988 (Box 2)
    - Puss in Boots, 1989-2005 (Box 2)
    - Quest for Beer, 1991-1995 (Box 2)
    - Reflection in a Window, 1989-1994 (Box 2)
    - Renegade (revised version), 1987-2005 (Box 2)
    - The Rose (Fire Kwatz), 1976-1984 (Box 2)
    - Rough Times in Laketown, 1974-1985 (Box 2)
    - Scream, 1977-1986 (Box 2)
    - Shape-Shifter, 1975-1981 (Box 2)
    - Shiva Shiva, 1984-1986 (Box 2)
    - The Singing Superheroes of France, 1985-1987 (Box 2)
    - The Sins of the Fathers, 1974-1981 (Box 2)
    - Slightly Pre-Kwatz, 1975-1986 (Box 2)
    - The Sparking Sea, Undated (Box 3)
    - The Story of Three Cities, 1971-1983 (Box 3)
    - The Student, 1973-1985 (Box 3)
    - Sweet Dreams, 1974-1980 (Box 3)
    - The Third Wave, 1981-1995 (Box 3)
    - Two Bad Dogs, 1990 (Box 3)
    - Two Materials of Time and Space, 1974-1975 (Box 3)
    - Two Plotting Pods, 1980-1988 (Box 3)
    - War Games, 1975-1988 (Box 3)
    - Water Kwatz, or More Bible, Suckers, 1975-1995 (Box 3)
    - What Happened on the Edge, 1973-1989 (Box 3)
    - Whores, 1979-1989 (Box 3)
    - Three Women and the Men, 1988-1989 (Box 3)
    - Xerox Room, 1973-1988 (Box 3)
    - The Young Shaman, 1976-1983 (Box 3)
    - The Man Who Came Awake, Undated (Box 3)
    - Pyramid Timestep, Undated (Box 3)
    - Adventuresome Journey, 2001; 2 folders (Box 4)
    - American Fairy Tales Short Story Collection, Undated (Box 4)
    - Mother Earth Blues, 1986-1987 (Box 5)
    - New Improved Beach Ball (new proposal), 1988 (Box 5)
    - [Notebook 1], Undated (Box 5)
    - [Notebook 2], Undated (Box 5)
    - [Notebook 3], Undated (Box 5)
    - [Notebook 4 and loose paper], Undated (Box 5)
    - [Notebook 5], Undated (Box 5)
    - [Notebook 6], Undated (Box 5)
    - [Notebook 8 and loose paper], Undated (Box 5)
    - [Notebook 9], Undated (Box 5)
    - [Notebook 11], Undated (Box 5)
    - [Notebook 12], Undated (Box 5)
    - [Notebook 13], Undated (Box 5)
    - [Notebook 14], Undated (Box 5)
    - [Notebook 15], Undated (Box 5)
    - [Notebook 16], Undated (Box 5)
    - [Notebook 17], Undated (Box 5)
    - [Notebook 18], Undated (Box 5)
    - [Notebook 19], Undated (Box 5)
    - [Notebook 20], Undated (Box 6)
    - [Notebook 21], Undated (Box 6)
    - [Notebook 22], Undated (Box 6)
  - Poems
    - [Notebook 7 and loose paper], Undated (Box 5)
    - Poems, Illustrated Poems, Essays, Misc, Undated (Box 5)
  - Essays
    - Time Travel, 1984-1988 (Box 3)
    - The Completion of Christianity, Undated (Box 3)
    - The End of War, Undated (Box 3)
    - Eulogy for Terry Carr and Generic Obituary, Undated (Box 3)
    - The Idea of Death, 1986 (Box 3)
    - New SF, 1986 (Box 3)
    - Non Atman, Undated (Box 3)
    - Silly White-Opp, 1988 (Box 3)
    - Spaced Out, 1989 (Box 3)
  - Song Lyrics
    - Music- Song Lyrics, Undated (Box 3)
    - [Notebook 10], Undated (Box 5)
    - [Contents of Audiovisual Files], Undated (Box 9)
    - Songs from the White Guardian, Undated (Box 9, Dvd RL11756-DVD-0001)
    - Songs from the White Guardian Written and performed by Ronald Anthony Cross, Undated (Box 9, Audio-cassette RL11756-CS-0001)
  - Novels
    - The First Guardian, Undated; 3 folders (Box 4)
    - First Guardian Printout, 1999 (Box 4)
    - Lost Guardian Outline, Undated (Box 4)
    - Beyond the Gods, Undated; 2 folders (Box 4)
    - Death Valley, Undated; 2 folders (Box 4)
    - The Girl Who Saved the World, 1988-1991 (Box 4)
    - Hotel and Mind Slaves Novel Proposal, 1977-1990 (Box 4)
    - Hunting Party, 2002; 2 folders (Box 5)
    - Isle of No Return Outline, 2002 (Box 5)
    - Pyramid Timestep, 2002 (Box 5)
    - Whores, 1988-1994 (Box 5)
  - Published Work
    - Books written by Cross
      - The Fourth Guardian (paperback), 1994 (Box 10)
      - The Fourth Guardian (softback), 1994 March (Box 10)
      - The Lost Guardian (paperback), 1995 (Box 10)
      - The Lost Guardian (hardback), 1995 (Box 10)
      - Prisoners of Paradise, 1988 (Box 10)
      - The White Guardian (softback), 1999 June (Box 10)
      - The White Guardian (hardback), 1998 June (Box 10)
    - Books with Cross as contributor
      - Airfish, 1993 (Box 10)
      - Alpha Gallery, 1990 (Box 10)
      - The Berkley Showcase Vol. 1, 1980 April (Box 10)
      - The Berkley Showcase Vol. 3, 1981 January (Box 10)
      - The Berkley Showcase Vol. 4, 1981 July (Box 10)
      - The Berkley Showcase Vol. 5, 1982 October (Box 10)
      - Das Fest des heiligen Dionysos, 1984 (Box 10)
      - Fantasy & Science Fiction, 1987 September (Box 10)
      - Fantasy & Science Fiction, 1988 October (Box 10)
      - Fantasy & Science Fiction, 1989 May (Box 10)
      - Fantasy & Science Fiction, 1990 March (Box 10)
      - Fantasy & Science Fiction, 1990 June (Box 10)
      - Fantasy & Science Fiction, 1990 September (Box 10)
      - Fantasy & Science Fiction, 1990 December (Box 10)
      - Fantasy & Science Fiction, 1991 May (Box 10)
      - Fantasy & Science Fiction, 1991 August (Box 10)
      - Far Frontiers, 1985 Winter (Box 10)
      - Future Pastimes, 1977 (Box 10)
      - In the Field of Fire (paperback), 1987 November (Box 10)
      - In the Field of Fire (softback), 1987 February (Box 10)
      - In the Field of Fire (hardback), 1987 February (Box 10)
      - Isaac Asimov's SF-Lite, 1993 March (Box 10)
      - Isaac Asimov's Werewolves, 1999 (Box 10)
      - Kopernikus 10, 1984 (Box 11)
      - New Worlds #5, 1973 (Box 11)
      - New Worlds #6, 1974 (Box 11)
      - New Worlds 6, 1973 (Box 11)
      - New Worlds 7, 1974 (Box 11)
      - Orbit 20, 1978 (Box 11)
      - Other Worlds, 1979 (Box 11)
      - Psypherboria, 1986 Summer (Box 11)
      - Psypherboria 4, 1987 Spring (Box 11)
      - Psypherboria 5, 1987 Early Summer (Box 11)
      - Psypherboria 7, 1987 Winter (Box 11)
      - Psypherboria 9, 1988 Summer (Box 11)
      - Psypherboria 11, 1988 Winter (Box 11)
      - Pulphouse Issue 2, 1988 (Box 11)
      - Pulphouse Issue 3, 1989 Spring (Box 11)
      - Pulphouse Issue 6, 1990 (Box 11)
      - ["Rampike" Publication of American Fairy Tales #1], 1986 (Box 7)
      - Tales from Issac Asimov's Science Fiction Magazine, 1986 (Box 11)
      - Universe 16, 1986 (Box 11)
      - The Vietnam War in American Stories, Songs, and Poems, 1996 (Box 11)
      - Weird Tales (paperback), 1988 Summer (Box 11)
      - Weird Tales (bound), 1988 Summer (Box 11)
      - Weird Tales (paperback), 1988 Fall (Box 11)
      - Weird Tales (bound), 1988 Fall (Box 11)
      - Weird Tales (paperback), 1991 Fall (Box 11)
      - Weird Tales (bound), 1991 Fall (Box 11)
      - Wet Visions, 1988 (Box 11)
    - Magazines with Cross as contributor
      - After Hours #25, 1995 Winter (Box 12)
      - Eternity Science Fiction, vol. 1, no. 2, 1980 (Box 12)
      - Fantasy Book, 1983 February (Box 12)
      - Isaac Asimov's Science Fiction Magazine, 1983 March (Box 12)
      - Isaac Asimov's Science Fiction Magazine, 1984 May (Box 12)
      - Isaac Asimov's Science Fiction Magazine, 1984 October (Box 12)
      - Isaac Asimov's Science Fiction Magazine, 1989 May (Box 12)
      - Isaac Asimov's Science Fiction Magazine, 1989 November (Box 12)
      - Isaac Asimov's Science Fiction Magazine, 1990 September (Box 12)
      - Last Wave, 1984 Winter (Box 12)
      - Last Wave, 1984 Autumn (Box 12)
      - New Pathways, 1990 September (Box 12)
      - Science Fiction Age, 1993 January (Box 12)
      - Trumpet, 1981 Summer (Box 12)
- Research, undated
  Includes primarily research Cross conducted for his published books. Among the material are style sheets; notes, lists, and questions regarding the works; photocopies of internet and other research completed, and reference materials. Includes some correspondence with publishers. There is a review of White Guardian, and a list of Cross' recommended readings.
  - "Read This", Undated (Box 3)
  - Adventuresome Journey Notes and Questions, Undated (Box 4)
  - First Guardian Notes and Questions, Undated (Box 4)
  - Fourth G. Notes, etc., Undated (Box 4)
  - Fourth Guardians- Questions, Undated (Box 4)
  - Lost Guardian Notes and Questions, Undated (Box 4)
  - Lost Guardian Reference, Materials, and Lists, Undated (Box 4)
  - Lost Guardian Biblio, Notes, Questions, etc., Undated (Box 4)
  - Xerox Info re Richard, Durnstein Pics, etc., Undated (Box 4)
  - White G Notes, Questions and Correspondence, Undated (Box 4)
  - White G- Review in Realms of Fantasy, Undated (Box 4)
- Correspondence, 1972-2019 and undated
  Includes correspondence regarding the publishing and review of Crosses work, along with contracts. Cross also comments on the work of other writers and his own unpublished work. In addition, there are files on royalty statements and the Nebula Awards. Material dated past Cross' death involves republication of his work.
  - JJ Beals Buisness, 2001 (Box 3)
  - Music Copyright, 1973-1992 (Box 3)
  - Agencja Praw Autorskitch, 1986-1987 (Box 3)
  - Hans Alpers- Utoprop, 1982-1991 (Box 3)
  - Berkley Books, 1979-1983 (Box 3)
  - Bibliographies and Lists and Foreign Republishes, 2019 (Box 3)
  - Carr, Terry, 1986 (Box 3)
  - Chocolak, Misha, 1988-1989 (Box 3)
  - Contracts, misc. (Stories, etc.), 1982-1995 (Box 3)
  - Mailed to Richard Curtis, 2001 (Box 3)
  - Curtis, Richard, 1988-1994 (Box 3)
  - Edelman, Scott, 1986-2001 (Box 3)
  - Edelstein, Scott, Undated (Box 3)
  - F and SF: Return of Copyrights, 1994 (Box 3)
  - Ferman, Ed (F and SF), 1994 (Box 3)
  - Frenkel, Jim, 1990-2001 (Box 3)
  - Frenkel and Henshan Notes and Phone calls, 2001-2004 (Box 3)
  - General Correspondence, 1980-1995 (Box 3)
  - Henshaw, RIch, 1994-2003 (Box 3)
  - Mooscock, Michael and Bailey, Hillary, 1974-1978 (Box 3)
  - Platt, Charles, 1972-1979 (Box 3)
  - Platt, Charles, 1986-1989 (Box 3)
  - Pohl, Frederik, 1974-1977 (Box 3)
  - Reviews, 1981-2011 (Box 3)
  - Rusch, Kris, 1989-1992 (Box 3)
  - Schweitzer, Darrell, 1985 (Box 3)
  - Silbersack, Jonn, 1979-1988 (Box 3)
  - Tanaka, Yohsiyuki, 1985-1987 (Box 3)
  - Torgeson, Roy, 1978-1981 (Box 3)
  - Von Gelder, Gordon, 1993 (Box 3)
  - Royalty Statements, 2001-2004 (Box 3)
  - Nebula Awards, 1989-1991 (Box 3)
  - Adventuresome Journey Inc. (submission record), 1986-2001 (Box 4)
  - Prisoners of Paradise Contracts, 1987-2005 (Box 4)
  - Fourth G: Copyright and Contract, 1993 (Box 4)
  - White G and Fallen G and First Guardian Contracts, 1994 (Box 4)
  - Lost G: Songs, 1994-1995 (Box 4)
  - Foreign Agency Copies of Contracts and Cancellations, Undated (Box 4)
  - American Fairy Tales Short Stories, Undated (Box 4)
  - Beyond the Gods, 1977-1993 (Box 4)
  - Death Valley (Blues), 2004 (Box 4)
  - Getting Out, 1985-1994 (Box 4)
  - The Fourth Guardian, 1983-1985 (Box 4)
  - Lost Guardian Correspondence, 1995 (Box 4)
  - White G Press Release to UCLA Library News, Undated (Box 4)
  - White G Promo Letters and Copies and Tapes, 1998 (Box 4)
  - White G- Catalog Copy from TOR Catalog, Undated (Box 4)
  - Prisoners of Paradise Author Questions and Misc, 1988 (Box 5)
  - Prisoners of Paradise Misc, 1988 (Box 5)
  - Prisoners of Paradise- Bruin Review and Interview, 1988 (Box 5)
  - The Show Portrait Outline, 2001-2005 (Box 5)
  - Vicious Circles, 1976 (Box 5)